CHARLIE BROOKE O'HARA

805.403.3066

charliebohara.com

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Data engineer experienced with writing Python and Bash scripts for automation, working with AWS infrastructure, and building Apache Hadoop MapReduce, Pig, and Spark applications. Self-starter who is quick to learn new technologies and capable of building applications with little guidance. Always ready to jump in and help the team, and consistently provide stellar service to stakeholders. Earned a 92% on the AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate exam, proving a strong ability to absorb and retain information.

EXPERIENCE

Software Engineer - Data Infrastructure, Verve

San Diego, CA — July 2017 - present

- Built an automated pipeline involving a Python script running on an AWS EC2
 instance that monitors for new AWS S3/SQS input, launches Hadoop MapReduce
 Java applications into AWS EMR to transform new input and merge into an internal
 AWS S3 dataset, and register status updates to an AWS RDS MySQL control table
- Manage a pipeline of Apache Spark jobs linked together with Python's Luigi module
- Write Bash scripts to launch ad-hoc Hadoop Streaming, Apache Pig, and Snowflake jobs to automate operational processes in order to streamline delivery
- Work with a team to establish a workflow for building, distributing, and ultimately executing against Python and Java code artifacts within our ecosystem

Big Data Engineer, Algebraix Data

San Diego, CA — February 2017 - July 2017

- Built and ran Apache Spark SQL and PySpark applications in AWS EMR to test proprietary query acceleration algorithm against TPC-H and TPC-DS benchmarks
- Wrote Bash scripts to streamline product installation in a variety of environments
- Wrote Python scripts for general automation and log analysis

Quality Assurance Engineer, Grizzly

San Diego, CA — September 2016 - February 2017

- Setup and built client WordPress applications leveraging Docker
- Wrote PHPUnit tests that were integrated with a continuous integration tool
- Wrote Python scripts for data mining, cleaning, analysis, and transfer

Junior Software Engineer Apprenticeship, The Firehose Project

Remote — March 2016 - August 2016

- Worked with a remote team to build a Ruby on Rails chess web application following agile methodologies with pair programming collaboration
- Built complex business logic for chess piece movements thorough test-driven development using RSpec
- Leverage jQuery User Interface and AJAX to move pieces in the browser and Pusher websocket for communication between players

TECHNICAL

charlie.b.ohara@gmail.com

linkedin.com/in/cbohara

PYTHON PYTEST

SKILLS

JAVA

SPARK HADOOP PIG

SQL SNOWFLAKE

LINUX CLI BASH SCRIPTING

DOCKER JENKINS

RUBY RUBY ON RAILS RSPEC

WORDPRESS PHPUNIT

HTML CSS JAVASCRIPT

GIT

EDUCATION

University of California, Santa Barbara

Bachelor's - Biology